So, I lead a team at Google that works on machine intelligence;
حسنا، أقود فريقاً في غوغل يعمل في مجال الذكاء الاصطناعي؛
in other words, the engineering discipline of making computers and devices
بعبارة أخرى، النظام الهندسي لصنع الحواسيب والأجهزة
able to do some of the things that brains do.
القادرة علي القيام ببعض الأمور التي يفعلها الدماغ.
And this makes us interested in real brains
وهذا مايجعلنا مهتمين بالدماغ الطبيعي
and neuroscience as well,
وعلم الأعصاب علي حد سواء،
and especially interested in the things that our brains do
ونهتم بشكل خاص بالأمور التي تقوم بها أدمغتنا
that are still far superior to the performance of computers.
والتي ما تزال متفوقة جداُ علي أداء الحواسيب.
Historically, one of those areas has been perception,
تاريخياً، كان الإدراك أحد تلك الأشياء،
the process by which things out there in the world --
وهي العملية التي من خلالها يمكن للأشياء المحيطة --
sounds and images --
كالأصوات والصور --
can turn into concepts in the mind.
أن تتحول إلي أفكار في العقل.
This is essential for our own brains,
وهذا أساسي لأدمغتنا،
and it's also pretty useful on a computer.
وأيضاً مفيد جداً في الحواسيب.
The machine perception algorithms, for example, that our team makes,
خوارزميات الإدراك الآليه، على سبيل المثال، التي يصنعها فريقنا،
are what enable your pictures on Google Photos to become searchable,
هي مايجعل صورك على محرك بحث غوغل للصور قابلة للبحث،
based on what's in them.
بناءً علي محتوياتها.
The flip side of perception is creativity:
الوجة الآخر للإدراك هو الإبداع:
turning a concept into something out there into the world.
أن تحول مفهوماً ما إلى شئ ملموس يهم العالم.
So over the past year, our work on machine perception
لذك خلال العام الماضي، فإن عملنا في الإدراك الإصطناعي
has also unexpectedly connected with the world of machine creativity
قد اقترن على نحو غير متوقع بالإبداع الآلي
and machine art.
والفن الآلي.
I think Michelangelo had a penetrating insight
أعتقد أن (مايكل أنجلو) كان يملك بصيرةً نافذة
into to this dual relationship between perception and creativity.
في هذه العلاقة الثنائية بين الإدراك والإبداع.
This is a famous quote of his:
هذه مقولة مشهورة نقلاً عنه:
"Every block of stone has a statue inside of it,
"كل كتلة حجرية تحمل في داخها تمثالاً
and the job of the sculptor is to discover it."
ومهمة النحات هي أن يكتشفه".
So I think that what Michelangelo was getting at
لذا أعتقد أن مايرمي اليه (مايكل أنجلو) هو
is that we create by perceiving,
أننا نبدع بمدى استيعابنا،
and that perception itself is an act of imagination
وأن الإدراك ذاته هو عملية تخيل
and is the stuff of creativity.
وهو أيضاً أداة الإبداع.
The organ that does all the thinking and perceiving and imagining,
العضو الذي يقوم بكل التفكير والإستيعاب والتخيّل،
of course, is the brain.
هو بالطبع، الدماغ.
And I'd like to begin with a brief bit of history
و أودّ أن أبدأ بنبذه تاريخية قصيرة
about what we know about brains.
عن ما نعرفه عن الدماغ.
Because unlike, say, the heart or the intestines,
لأنه، خلافاً لمثلاً، القلب أو الأمعاء.
you really can't say very much about a brain by just looking at it,
لا يمكنك قول الكثير عن الدماغ بمجرد النظر اليه،
at least with the naked eye.
على الأقل بالعين المجردة.
The early anatomists who looked at brains
علماء التشريج الأوائل الذين نظروا في الدماغ
gave the superficial structures of this thing all kinds of fanciful names,
منحوا البنى السطحية للدماغ جميع المصطلحات المبهرجة،
like hippocampus, meaning "little shrimp."
مثل الحصين، الذي يعني "الجمبري الصغير."
But of course that sort of thing doesn't tell us very much
وبالطبع هذا النمط من الأمور لا يخبرنا بالكثير
about what's actually going on inside.
عن ما يحدث في الداخل.
The first person who, I think, really developed some kind of insight
أعتقد بحق، أن أول من قام بتكوين نوع من البصيرة
into what was going on in the brain
عما يحدث داخل الدماغ
was the great Spanish neuroanatomist, Santiago Ramón y Cajal,
كان عالم تشريح الأعصاب العظيم (سانتياغو رامون كاخال)،
in the 19th century,
في القرن التاسع عشر،
who used microscopy and special stains
و الذي استخدم المجهر وأصبغة خاصة
that could selectively fill in or render in very high contrast
و التي كان بإمكانها أن تملأ الخلايا المفردة في الدماغ
the individual cells in the brain,
بتباينٍ شديد الوضوح،
in order to start to understand their morphologies.
من أجل البدء بفهم تكوينها الشكلي.
And these are the kinds of drawings that he made of neurons
و هذه هي أنواع الرسومات التي ابتكرها من الخلايا العصبية
in the 19th century.
في القرن التاسع عشر.
This is from a bird brain.
هذا من دماغ طائر.
And you see this incredible variety of different sorts of cells,
ويمكنك رؤية التنوع الرائع لمختلف أنواع الخلايا،
even the cellular theory itself was quite new at this point.
حتى النظرية الخلوية نفسها كانت حديثة العهد في تلك المرحلة.
And these structures,
وهذه البنى،
these cells that have these arborizations,
هذه الخلايا التي لديها هذه التغصنات النهائية،
these branches that can go very, very long distances --
هذه التفرعات التي يمكنها أن تتمدد لمسافات طويلة جداً جداً
this was very novel at the time.
كان أمراً غير مألوف في تلك الحقبة.
They're reminiscent, of course, of wires.
بالطبع، إنها أسلاك حافلة بالذكريات،.
That might have been obvious to some people in the 19th century;
قد يبدو الأمر واضحاً للبعض في القرن 19؛
the revolutions of wiring and electricity were just getting underway.
ثورة الأسلاك و الكهرباء كانت لا تزال قيد البناء.
But in many ways,
لكن في العديد من النواحي،
these microanatomical drawings of Ramón y Cajal's, like this one,
كانت هذه الرسومات المجهرية ل(رامون كاخال) كهذه الرسمة،
they're still in some ways unsurpassed.
كانت لا تزال بشكل ما متعثرة الخطى.
We're still more than a century later,
ولا نزال بعد أكثر من قرن،
trying to finish the job that Ramón y Cajal started.
نحاول إنهاء المهمة التي بدأها (رامون كاخال).
These are raw data from our collaborators
هذه بيانات خام من مساعدينا
at the Max Planck Institute of Neuroscience.
في معهد ماكس بلانك لعلم الأعصاب.
And what our collaborators have done
وما فعله مساعدونا
is to image little pieces of brain tissue.
هو رسم أجزاء صغيرة من نسيج دماغي.
The entire sample here is about one cubic millimeter in size,
حجم العينة الكاملة هنا حوالي ميليميتر مكعب واحد،
and I'm showing you a very, very small piece of it here.
هنا أريكم جزءاً صغيراً جداً جداً منها.
That bar on the left is about one micron.
طول الخط الموجود إلى اليسار حوالي مايكرون واحد.
The structures you see are mitochondria
البنى التي ترونها هي الجسيمات الكوندرية (ميتوكوندريا)
that are the size of bacteria.
و هي بحجم الباكتريا.
And these are consecutive slices
و هذه شرائح متلاحقة
through this very, very tiny block of tissue.
خلال كتلة النسيج هذه المتناهية في الصغر.
Just for comparison's sake,
و على سبيل المقارنة فقط،
the diameter of an average strand of hair is about 100 microns.
فإن قطر خصلة شعر عادية حوالي 100 مايكرون.
So we're looking at something much, much smaller
و بهذا فإننا ننظر إلى شئ أصغر بكثيرٍ جداً
than a single strand of hair.
من خصلة شعر واحدة.
And from these kinds of serial electron microscopy slices,
و من خلال هذه الأنواع من الشرائح المأخوذة بمجهر إلكتروني تسلسلي،
one can start to make reconstructions in 3D of neurons that look like these.
يمكن للمرء أن يبدأ العمل على إعادة بناء نموذج ثلاثي الأبعاد لخلية عصبية تبدو كهذه.
So these are sort of in the same style as Ramón y Cajal.
إذاً هذه أنماط مشابهة نوعاً ما لتلك التي لدى (رامون كاخال).
Only a few neurons lit up,
و قد ظهرت بضع خلايا عصبية فقط،
because otherwise we wouldn't be able to see anything here.
و إلا ما كنا لنستطيع أن نرى أي شيء هنا.
It would be so crowded,
كانت لتبدو شديدة الإزدحام،
so full of structure,
غنية بالتركيب،
of wiring all connecting one neuron to another.
و الوصلات التي تربط الخلايا العصبية ببعضها البعض.
So Ramón y Cajal was a little bit ahead of his time,
بهذا كان (رامون كاخال) سابقاً لعصره بعض الشيء،
and progress on understanding the brain
و متقدماً في فهمه للدماغ
proceeded slowly over the next few decades.
تابع ببطئ خلال العقود اللاحقة.
But we knew that neurons used electricity,
و لكننا علمنا أن الخلايا العصبية استخدمت الكهرباء،
and by World War II, our technology was advanced enough
و بحلول الحرب العالمية الثانية، تطورت تقنياتنا على نحو كافٍ
to start doing real electrical experiments on live neurons
للبدء بإجراء تجارب كهربائية فعلية على خلايا عصبية حية
to better understand how they worked.
من أجل زيادة فهمنا لكيفية عملها.
This was the very same time when computers were being invented,
و في ذات الفترة تماماً بدأ اختراع الحواسيب.
very much based on the idea of modeling the brain --
و قد اعتمدت الفكرة إلى حد كبير على نمذجة الدماغ --
of "intelligent machinery," as Alan Turing called it,
"الآلة الذكية،" كما أطلق عليها (ألان تورينغ)،
one of the fathers of computer science.
أحد آباء علم الحاسوب.
Warren McCulloch and Walter Pitts looked at Ramón y Cajal's drawing
اتطلع (وارن ماكولوكش) و(والتر بيتس) على رسومات (رامون كاخال)
of visual cortex,
لمنطقة القشرة البصرية،
which I'm showing here.
التي أعرضها هنا.
This is the cortex that processes imagery that comes from the eye.
هذه هي القشرة التي تقوم بمعالجة الصور القادمة من العين.
And for them, this looked like a circuit diagram.
و بالنسبة لهما، بدا هذا كمخطط دارة كهربائية.
So there are a lot of details in McCulloch and Pitts's circuit diagram
و بهذا ثمة الكثير من التفاصيل في مخطط الدارة لكل من (ماكولوتش) و(بيتس)
that are not quite right.
ليست صحيحة تماماً.
But this basic idea
لكن هذه الفكرة الأساسية
that visual cortex works like a series of computational elements
أن القشرة الدماغية البصرية تعمل كسلسلة من العناصر الحاسوبية
that pass information one to the next in a cascade,
التي تمرر المعلومات من عنصر إلى التالي بتسلسل،
is essentially correct.
هي فكرة صحيحة أساساً.
Let's talk for a moment
دعونا نتكلم لبرهة
about what a model for processing visual information would need to do.
عن النموذج المطلوب من أجل معالجة المعلومات البصرية.
The basic task of perception
المهمة الأساسية للإدراك
is to take an image like this one and say,
هي أخذ صورة كهذه والقول،
"That's a bird,"
"ذلك طائر،"
which is a very simple thing for us to do with our brains.
و هو أمر في غاية السهولة بالنسبة لنا باستخدام أدمغتنا.
But you should all understand that for a computer,
و لكن ما عليكم أن تفهموه هو أنه بالنسبة لحاسوب،
this was pretty much impossible just a few years ago.
فإن هذا الأمر كان من المحال تحقيقه قبل بضعة سنوات قليلة.
The classical computing paradigm
لم يكن نموذج الحاسوب التقليدي
is not one in which this task is easy to do.
واحداً يمكن من خلاله تحقيق هذه المهمة بسهولة.
So what's going on between the pixels,
إذاً إن ما يحدث بين نقاط البيكسل،
between the image of the bird and the word "bird,"
بين صورة الطائر، و كلمة "طائر،"
is essentially a set of neurons connected to each other
أساساً هو مجموعة من العصبونات المرتبطة ببعضها
in a neural network,
ضمن شبكة عصبونية،
as I'm diagramming here.
كما أعرضها هنا.
This neural network could be biological, inside our visual cortices,
يمكن لهذه الشبكة العصبونية أن تكون حيوية، ضمن القشرة الدماغية البصرية،
or, nowadays, we start to have the capability
أو، حالياً، نبدأ العمل على إمكانية
to model such neural networks on the computer.
نمذجة شبكات عصبونية مماثلة في الحاسوب.
And I'll show you what that actually looks like.
و سوف أريكم حقيقة كيف تبدو تلك الشبكات.
So the pixels you can think about as a first layer of neurons,
إذاً يمكنك تصور نقاط البيكسل كطبقة أولى من العصبونات،
and that's, in fact, how it works in the eye --
و هذا، في الواقع، كيفية عملها في العين --
that's the neurons in the retina.
تلك هي العصبونات في الشبكية.
And those feed forward
و تلك العصبونات تلقم الإشارة
into one layer after another layer, after another layer of neurons,
داخل طبقة بعد طبقة أخرى، بعد طبقة أخرى من العصبونات،
all connected by synapses of different weights.
جميعها مرتبطة بواسطة مشابك ذات أوزان مختلفة.
The behavior of this network
إن سلوك هذه الشبكة
is characterized by the strengths of all of those synapses.
تتميز عن طريق قوة جميع تلك المشابك.
Those characterize the computational properties of this network.
و هذه تميز السمات الحسابية لهذه الشبكة.
And at the end of the day,
وبنهاية المطاف،
you have a neuron or a small group of neurons
يغدو لديك عصبون أو مجموعة صغيرة من العصبونات
that light up, saying, "bird."
التي تضيء، كلمة، "طائر."
Now I'm going to represent those three things --
سأقوم الآن بتمثيل تلك الأمور الثلاث --
the input pixels and the synapses in the neural network,
المدخلات بيكسلات والمشابك في الشبكة العصبية،
and bird, the output --
و طائر، المخرجات --
by three variables: x, w and y.
تحدد بمتغيرات ثلاث: x وw وy
There are maybe a million or so x's --
ربما ثمة مليون أو نحو ذلك من المتغير x
a million pixels in that image.
مليون بيكسل في تلك الصورة.
There are billions or trillions of w's,
ثمة مليونات أو ترليونات من المتغير w،
which represent the weights of all these synapses in the neural network.
التي تمثل وزن جميع هذه المشابك في الشبكة العصبية.
And there's a very small number of y's,
و يوجد كم ضئيل من المتغير y،
of outputs that that network has.
من المخرجات التي تمتلكها الشبكة.
"Bird" is only four letters, right?
"طائر" هي كلمة من أربعة أحرف، صحيح؟
So let's pretend that this is just a simple formula,
إذاً دعونا نتظاهر بأن هذه مجرد معادلة بسيطة،
x "x" w = y.
x" x" w = y.
I'm putting the times in scare quotes
أضع التكرار ضمن إشارتي اقتباس مخيفتين
because what's really going on there, of course,
لأن ما يحدث بالفعل هناك، بالطبع،
is a very complicated series of mathematical operations.
عبارة عن سلاسل معقدة من العمليات الحسابية الرياضية.
That's one equation.
تلك معادلة واحدة.
There are three variables.
يوجد ثلاثة متغيرات.
And we all know that if you have one equation,
و جميعنا نعلم أنه عندما يكون لدينا معادلة واحدة،
you can solve one variable by knowing the other two things.
يمكنكم حل أحد المتغيرات بمعرفة المتغيرين الآخرين.
So the problem of inference,
لذلك فإن مشكلة الاستدلال،
that is, figuring out that the picture of a bird is a bird,
هي أن نعلم أن صورة الطائر هي طائر،
is this one:
هي هذه:
it's where y is the unknown and w and x are known.
هي أن المتغير y مجهول، والمتغيرين w و x معلومان.
You know the neural network, you know the pixels.
أنتم تعرفون الشبكات العصبية، تعرفون البيكسلات.
As you can see, that's actually a relatively straightforward problem.
كما ترون، تلك هي مشكلة بسيطة نسبياً.
You multiply two times three and you're done.
تضاعفون مرتين بثلاث وتنتهون.
I'll show you an artificial neural network
سأريكم شبكة عصبية اصطناعية
that we've built recently, doing exactly that.
قمنا ببنائها مؤخراً، بنفس الأسلوب تماماً.
This is running in real time on a mobile phone,
تعمل بالزمن الحقيقي على الهاتف المحمول،
and that's, of course, amazing in its own right,
و هذا، بالطبع، أمر رائع بحد ذاته،
that mobile phones can do so many billions and trillions of operations
الهاتف النقال يستطيع القيام بمليارات بل ترليونات العمليات
per second.
بالثانية.
What you're looking at is a phone
ما تنظر اليه هو هاتف
looking at one after another picture of a bird,
تنظر لصورة تلو الأخرى لطائر،
and actually not only saying, "Yes, it's a bird,"
وفي الحقيقية، لا تقول فقط "نعم، إنه طائر"
but identifying the species of bird with a network of this sort.
بل تميّز نوع الطائر بشبكة من هذا النوع.
So in that picture,
اذاً في تلك الصورة،
the x and the w are known, and the y is the unknown.
ال x وw معروفان، بينما y غير معروفة.
I'm glossing over the very difficult part, of course,
أنا أموه حول الجزء الصعب كما ترون
which is how on earth do we figure out the w,
اذاً كيف من الممكن أن نميز w،
the brain that can do such a thing?
الدماغ الذي يستطيع القيام بشيء كهذا؟
How would we ever learn such a model?
كيف يمكننا تعلم هذا النموذج؟
So this process of learning, of solving for w,
إذاً عملية التعليم هذه، لحل w
if we were doing this with the simple equation
اذا ما كنا نقوم بهذا بمساعدة المعادلة البسيطة
in which we think about these as numbers,
والتي نعامل فيها هذه الأحرف كأرقام،
we know exactly how to do that: 6 = 2 x w,
نستطيع فهم ذلك تماماً 6 = 2 x w
well, we divide by two and we're done.
حسناً نقسم على اثنين وانتهينا.
The problem is with this operator.
المشكلة ستكون بهذه العملية.
So, division --
اذاً، القسمة --
we've used division because it's the inverse to multiplication,
استخدمنا القسمة ، لأنها عكس الضرب،
but as I've just said,
لكن كما قلت،
the multiplication is a bit of a lie here.
الضرب هو كذبة صغيرة هنا.
This is a very, very complicated, very non-linear operation;
هذه العملية معقدة للغاية، وهي عملية غير خطية
it has no inverse.
وليس لديها معكوس.
So we have to figure out a way to solve the equation
اذاً ،علينا إيجاد طريقة لحل هذه المعادلة
without a division operator.
بدون عملية قسمة.
And the way to do that is fairly straightforward.
والطريقة للقيام بذلك غير واضحة نوعاً ما.
You just say, let's play a little algebra trick,
لنقل، دعونا نقوم بلعبة جبرية ما
and move the six over to the right-hand side of the equation.
ولننقل الرقم ستة الى الجانب اليميني من المعادلة.
Now, we're still using multiplication.
الأن، مازلنا نستخدم عملية الضرب.
And that zero -- let's think about it as an error.
وذلك الصفر -- لنفكر به كأنه خطأ ما.
In other words, if we've solved for w the right way,
بعبارة أخرى، إذا حلينا المعادلة ل w بالطريقة الصحيحة،
then the error will be zero.
اذاً سيكون الخطأ صفراً.
And if we haven't gotten it quite right,
واذا لم نحلها حلاً صحيحاً،
the error will be greater than zero.
سيكون الخطأ أكبر من الصفر.
So now we can just take guesses to minimize the error,
الأن سوف نخمن حتى يكون الخطأ أصغر،
and that's the sort of thing computers are very good at.
وهذا هو الشيء الذي تبرع فيه أجهزة الحاسوب جداً.
So you've taken an initial guess:
اذاً، لناخذ تخميناً أولياً:
what if w = 0?
مائا لو w=0 ؟
Well, then the error is 6.
إذاً، الخطأ سيكون 6.
What if w = 1? The error is 4.
ماذا لو W=1 ؟ إذاً الخطأ 4 .
And then the computer can sort of play Marco Polo,
ومن ثم يستطيع الحاسوب أن يلعب (ماركو بولو)،
and drive down the error close to zero.
حتى يقوم بإنقاص الخطأ الى الصفر.
As it does that, it's getting successive approximations to w.
وبينما يفعل ذلك، فهو يحصل على قيمة تقريبة متعاقبة ل w.
Typically, it never quite gets there, but after about a dozen steps,
بالعادة ،لايصل الى هذه القيمة بسرعة لكن بعد الكثير من الخطوات،
we're up to w = 2.999, which is close enough.
نصل لحوالي w = 2.999 وهي قيمة تقريبية كافية.
And this is the learning process.
وهذه هي العملية التعليمية.
So remember that what's been going on here
اذاً تذكر ما كان يجري هنا
is that we've been taking a lot of known x's and known y's
كنا نقوم باخذ الكثير من قيم x و y المعلومة
and solving for the w in the middle through an iterative process.
ونقوم بحل w خلال عمليات متعاقبة.
It's exactly the same way that we do our own learning.
تماماً هي نفس الطريقة التي نتعلم بها.
We have many, many images as babies
تستصحب أذهاننا الكثير من صور فترة الطفولة
and we get told, "This is a bird; this is not a bird."
ويُقال لنا "هذا طائر، ليس هذا طائراً."
And over time, through iteration,
ومع مرور الوقت، ومع التكرار،
we solve for w, we solve for those neural connections.
نحل الw نقوم بالحل عن طريق تلك الوصلات العصبية.
So now, we've held x and w fixed to solve for y;
اذاً الأن، لدينا x و y كقيم ثابتة لكي نحل y ،
that's everyday, fast perception.
هذا ككل يوم، تصور سريع.
We figure out how we can solve for w,
نكتشف كيف نستطيع إيجاد الحل ل w،
that's learning, which is a lot harder,
ذلك هو التعلم، وهو الأكثر صعوبة،
because we need to do error minimization,
لأننا نحتاج إلى تصغير الخطأ،
using a lot of training examples.
باستخدام الكثير من أمثلة التعلم،
And about a year ago, Alex Mordvintsev, on our team,
ومنذ حوالي السنة، أحد أعضاء فريقنا (أليكس ماريفينسف)،
decided to experiment with what happens if we try solving for x,
قرر أن يجرب ماذا سيحدث إذا ما حاولنا حل المعادلة لأجل x،
given a known w and a known y.
بإعطاء قيمة معلومة ل w و y .
In other words,
بعبارة أخرى،
you know that it's a bird,
أنت تعرف أنه طائر،
and you already have your neural network that you've trained on birds,
وتتمتع مسبقاً بشبكة عصبية دربتها على أن الذي أمامك طائر،
but what is the picture of a bird?
لكن ما الذي تبدو عليه صورة الطائر؟
It turns out that by using exactly the same error-minimization procedure,
اتضح أنه باستخدام نفس عملية تقليل الخطأ،
one can do that with the network trained to recognize birds,
نستطيع فعل المثل عن طريق الشبكة المدربة على التعرف على الطيور،
and the result turns out to be ...
واتضح أن النتيجة ستكون ...
a picture of birds.
صورة لطيور.
So this is a picture of birds generated entirely by a neural network
هذه صورة لطائر تم توليدها كلياً بواسطة شبكة عصبية
that was trained to recognize birds,
والتي دُربت لتتعرف على الطيور.
just by solving for x rather than solving for y,
فقط بحل بالنسبة ل x بدل الحل بالنسبة ل y.
and doing that iteratively.
وبالقيام بتلك التكرارات.
Here's another fun example.
هنا مثال مسلي آخر.
This was a work made by Mike Tyka in our group,
هذا العمل صنعه (مايك تايكو) من فريقنا،
which he calls "Animal Parade."
والذي يدعوه "موكب الحيوانات".
It reminds me a little bit of William Kentridge's artworks,
ويذكرني قليلاً بأعمال (وليام كينتردوغ) الفنية،
in which he makes sketches, rubs them out,
حيث يقوم برسم نماذج، ثم يقوم بتحريكها،
makes sketches, rubs them out,
يرسم النماذج، ويحركها،
and creates a movie this way.
ويصنع فلم بهذه الطريقة.
In this case,
في هذه الحالة،
what Mike is doing is varying y over the space of different animals,
مايقوم به (مايك) هو تغيير y عبر مساحة متباينة من الحيوانات،
in a network designed to recognize and distinguish
ضمن شبكة مصصمة، لكي تميز وتعرف
different animals from each other.
الحيوانات المختلفة عن بعضها البعض.
And you get this strange, Escher-like morph from one animal to another.
وستحصل على هذا الشكل الغريب من حيوان لآخر،
Here he and Alex together have tried reducing
هو و(ألكس) حاولا تقليل
the y's to a space of only two dimensions,
ال y الى مساحة بعدين فقط،
thereby making a map out of the space of all things
مما سمح لهما بصنع خريطة من مساحة كل الأشياء
recognized by this network.
المُتعرف عليها من قبل هذه الشبكة.
Doing this kind of synthesis
بالقيام بهذا النوع من التركيب
or generation of imagery over that entire surface,
أو توليد صورة من ذلك السطح الكامل،
varying y over the surface, you make a kind of map --
بتغيير y عبر ذلك السطح، ستحصل على خريطة نوعاً ما --
a visual map of all the things the network knows how to recognize.
خريطة بصرية من كل الأشياء التي تستطيع الشبكة تمييزها.
The animals are all here; "armadillo" is right in that spot.
الحيوانات كلها موجودة هنا، و"أرمانديلو" في البقعة المناسبة.
You can do this with other kinds of networks as well.
وتستطيع القيام بذلك مع أنواع آخرى من الشبكات أيضاً.
This is a network designed to recognize faces,
هذه الشبكة مصممة لمعرفة الوجوه،
to distinguish one face from another.
لتميز كل وجه عن الآخر.
And here, we're putting in a y that says, "me,"
وهنا نقوم بوضع ال y التي تقول "أنا،"
my own face parameters.
مقاييس وجهي الخاصة.
And when this thing solves for x,
وعندما تُحل هذه الشبكة بالنسبة لx،
it generates this rather crazy,
بالأحرى تولد هذا الجنون،
kind of cubist, surreal, psychedelic picture of me
صورة تكعيبية، وسريالية، وغريبة لي
from multiple points of view at once.
من عدة وجهات نظر في نفس الوقت.
The reason it looks like multiple points of view at once
والسبب في تكوينها من عدة وجهات نظر في نفس الوقت
is because that network is designed to get rid of the ambiguity
هو أن هذه الشبكة صُممت لكي تتخلص من الغموض
of a face being in one pose or another pose,
الذي يلحق بالوجوه من وضعية تصوير لآخرى،
being looked at with one kind of lighting, another kind of lighting.
وبالنظر من وضع إضاءة الى آخر.
So when you do this sort of reconstruction,
إذاً حتى تقوم بهذا النوع من إعادة التكوين،
if you don't use some sort of guide image
اذا لم تستخدم نوع من الصور الدليلية
or guide statistics,
أو دليل إحصائي،
then you'll get a sort of confusion of different points of view,
حينها ستحصل على قليل من الإرتباك من نقاط مختلفة،
because it's ambiguous.
لأنه غامض.
This is what happens if Alex uses his own face as a guide image
هذا ما سيحصل إذا استخدم (أليكس) وجهه كصورة دليلية
during that optimization process to reconstruct my own face.
خلال عملية إعادة تكوين وجهي.
So you can see it's not perfect.
سترون بأنها ليست مثالية.
There's still quite a lot of work to do
وما يزال هناك الكثير من العمل لنقوم به
on how we optimize that optimization process.
لتحسين عملية إعادة التكوين هذه.
But you start to get something more like a coherent face,
لكن بدأنا بالحصول على شيء يشبه الوجه المتماسك،
rendered using my own face as a guide.
وذلك باستخدام وجهي كدليل.
You don't have to start with a blank canvas
ليس عليك البدء بقماش فارغ
or with white noise.
أو ضوضاء بيضاء.
When you're solving for x,
بحل المعادلة بالنسبة لx
you can begin with an x, that is itself already some other image.
تستطيع البدء بx والتي هي نفسها صورة ما مسبقاً.
That's what this little demonstration is.
هذا هو هذا المنظر الصغير.
This is a network that is designed to categorize
هذه شبكة مُصممة لكي تصنف
all sorts of different objects -- man-made structures, animals ...
العديد من الأشياء المختلفة أشخاص، أشكال، حيوانات ...
Here we're starting with just a picture of clouds,
هنا، بدأنا بصورة للغيوم،
and as we optimize,
وبينما نقوم بعملية الاستمثال،
basically, this network is figuring out what it sees in the clouds.
أساساً، هذه الشبكة تميز ما تراه بين الغيوم.
And the more time you spend looking at this,
وكلما استغرقت بالنظر الى هذا،
the more things you also will see in the clouds.
سترى المزيد من الأشياء بين الغيوم
You could also use the face network to hallucinate into this,
تستطيع أيضاً استخدام شبكة الوجوه لكي تهلوس الى هذا،
and you get some pretty crazy stuff.
وستحصل على أشياء مجنونة جداً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Or, Mike has done some other experiments
أو، أجرى (مايك) تجارب أخرى
in which he takes that cloud image,
حيث يأخذ صورة الغيمة هذه،
hallucinates, zooms, hallucinates, zooms hallucinates, zooms.
يهلوسها ويكبرها، يهلوسها ويكبرها، يهلوسها ويكبرها.
And in this way,
وبهذه الطريقة،
you can get a sort of fugue state of the network, I suppose,
نستطيع الحصول على حالة من الضباب لهذه الشبكة كما أعتقد،
or a sort of free association,
أو نوعاً ما من المجمعات الحرة،
in which the network is eating its own tail.
حيث تقوم الشبكات بتدمير نفسها.
So every image is now the basis for,
إذاً كل صورة هي الأساس لما
"What do I think I see next?
"ما الذي أعتقد أني سأراه بعدها؟
What do I think I see next? What do I think I see next?"
مالذي أعتقد أني سأراه بعدها؟
I showed this for the first time in public
عرضت هذا لأول مرة على الملأ
to a group at a lecture in Seattle called "Higher Education" --
لمجموعة خلال محاضرة في سياتل تحت عوان (التعليم العالي) --
this was right after marijuana was legalized.
كان هذا مباشرة بعد إجازة الماريجونا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I'd like to finish up quickly
إذاً، أريد أن أختم سريعاً
by just noting that this technology is not constrained.
بالإشارة الى أن هذه التكنولوجيا غير مقيدة
I've shown you purely visual examples because they're really fun to look at.
لقد أريتكم أمثلة بصرية بحتة لأنه من الممتع النظر اليها
It's not a purely visual technology.
لكنها ليست تقنية بصرية بحتة.
Our artist collaborator, Ross Goodwin,
الفنان المتعاون معنا، (روس غوردن)
has done experiments involving a camera that takes a picture,
قام بتجارب، تتضمن كاميرا تقوم بأخذ صورة،
and then a computer in his backpack writes a poem using neural networks,
ثم حاسوب في حقيبة ظهره يقوم بكتابة قصيدة باستخدام الشبكات العصبية،
based on the contents of the image.
وذلك استناداً على محتوى الصورة.
And that poetry neural network has been trained
وقد دُربت الشبكة العصبية الشعرية
on a large corpus of 20th-century poetry.
على أشعار كثيرة من القرن العشرين.
And the poetry is, you know,
والشعر كما تعلمون،
I think, kind of not bad, actually.
كما أعتقد، هذا ليس سيئاً في الواقع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
In closing,
في الختام،
I think that per Michelangelo,
أعتقد أن (مايكل أنجيلو)،
I think he was right;
كان على حق،
perception and creativity are very intimately connected.
الإدراك والإبداع مرتبطان ارتباطاً وثيقاً.
What we've just seen are neural networks
ما رأيناه للتو هو شبكات عصبية،
that are entirely trained to discriminate,
مُدربة كلياً لكي تميز،
or to recognize different things in the world,
أو للتعرف على الأشياء المختلفة في هذا العالم،
able to be run in reverse, to generate.
وقادرة على العمل في الإتجاه المعاكس، لتولد.
One of the things that suggests to me
وأحد الأشياء التي اقترحت لي
is not only that Michelangelo really did see
ليس فقط ما رأه (مايكل أنجيلو)
the sculpture in the blocks of stone,
المنحوتة في قطعة الحجر،
but that any creature, any being, any alien
لكن أي مخلوق، أي كائن، أي فضائي
that is able to do perceptual acts of that sort
يستطيع أن يقوم بأعمال حسية من هذا النوع
is also able to create
هو قادر أيضاً على التكوين
because it's exactly the same machinery that's used in both cases.
لأنها نفس الآلية المستخدمة في الحالتين.
Also, I think that perception and creativity are by no means
كذلك، أعتقد أن الإدراك والإبداع لا يعنيان بالضرورة
uniquely human.
إنسان على نحو مميز.
We start to have computer models that can do exactly these sorts of things.
بدأنا باختراع حواسيب تقوم بنفس هذه الأشياء.
And that ought to be unsurprising; the brain is computational.
ومن المفترض أن لا يكون ذلك مفاجئاً؛ فالدماغ في الأساس حسابي.
And finally,
وأخيراً،
computing began as an exercise in designing intelligent machinery.
بدأت الحوسبة كتدريب لتطويرألات ذكية.
It was very much modeled after the idea
وتم تغييرها على نحو كبير بعد فكرة
of how could we make machines intelligent.
كيف نستطيع جعل الآلات ذكية.
And we finally are starting to fulfill now
وأخيراً، بدأنا نوفي
some of the promises of those early pioneers,
ببعض وعود أولئك الرعيل الأول،
of Turing and von Neumann
ل(تورينج) و(فون نيومان)
and McCulloch and Pitts.
و(مكولوتش) و(بيتس).
And I think that computing is not just about accounting
وأعتقد أن الحوسبة لا تتعلق فقط بالحساب
or playing Candy Crush or something.
أو لعب الكاندي كراش أو شيء ما.
From the beginning, we modeled them after our minds.
من البداية، قمنا بأخذ أدمغتنا كنموذج.
And they give us both the ability to understand our own minds better
وأعطانا ذلك القابلية لفهم أدمغتنا فهماً أفضل
and to extend them.
ومدّها.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)